Guide to the Dola Wilson and Charles M. Boucher Papers 1939-1954
Montana Historical Society Archives
Dola Wilson and Charles M. Boucher Papers
1939-1954
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 324
Wilson, Dola, 1891-1972
1.5 linear feet of shelf space
Dola Wilson owned the Range Rider Bar and Cafe in Miles City. This collection (n.d., 1940s-1950s) consists of notes and biographical sketches concerning the local cowboys, or "Range Riders", which were collected and recorded for Wilson by his associate Charles Boucher. Dola arranged for Boucher, a local journalist to interview each of the "riders" and write biographical sketeches of their lives. The riders would then go across the street to the L. A. Huffman photo studio (later Stephenson Studio) to have their picture taken. [A biographical sketch of Dola Wilson is include in the accession record. Photographs of Range Riders were transferred to Photo Archives. Motion picture film was transferred by Photo Archives to the American Film Institute.]
Dola Wilson was born in Gaffney, South Carolina, in 1891, the son of Charles and Elizabeth Wilson. He came to Miles City, Montana, in 1912, and worked on a ranch for three years. He then worked for the Milwaukee Road. In 1934 he bought the Blue Ribbon Bar and re-named it the Range Riders Bar and Restaurant. To decorate his establishment he collected photographs of prominent area stockmen. In 1944 he began to compile biographical materials about the stockmen and attempted to expand the number of photographs. He hired Charles M. Boucher, a retired newspaperman, to research and write the biographical material. He retired in 1957 and his son Dola Jr. took over the bar. Dola Wilson Sr. died in November, 1972. Charles M. Boucher was born in Germantown, Pennsylvania, on July 16, 1864, the son of William F. Boucher. When Charles was two and a half, his father died leaving his mother with 5 young children. The family moved to her parents' farm at Terwood, Pennsylvania. In 1885 he graduated from Girard College, an institution endowed by financier Stephen Girard to educate white male orphans. The following year he apprenticed as a pattern maker. In 1892 he headed west to Nebraska. He went to work for his brother-in-law George Conn's Ogallala Record and Baxton Pilot. The following year year he moved to Miles City, Montana, and worked as a reporter, first for the Yellowstone Journal and later for the \ul Miles City Star. After his retirement he was engaged by Dola Wilson to write biographical sketches of the cowboys and ranchers whose photographs were in the Range Riders Bar and Cafe. He died in 1954.
Content Description:
Collection consists primarily of biographical notes, sketches, brand information, and obituaries concerning local cowboys and ranchers, which were collected and recorded for Wilson by his associate Charles Boucher. The files are arranged alphabetically. In addition, the collection contains a subject file on brands, several historical writings by Boucher and others, and numerous small notebooks, arranged chronologically, which contain notes for the biographical sketches, notes concerning Boucher's politics and philosophy, lists, and miscellany. [A biographical sketch of Dola Wilson is included in the accession record. Photographs of Range Riders were transferred to Photo Archives. Motion picture film was transferred by Photo Archives to the American Film Institute.]
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
A biographical sketch of Dola Wilson is include in the accession record. MHS photograph archives added the photographs from the donation to their collection and transferred manuscript material to the MHS archives. Motion picture film was transferred by Photo Archives to the American Film Institute.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Cattle brands
Cattle ranching--Montana
Cattle drives
Ranch life
Ranches
Chisholm Trail
Alzada (Mont.)
Custer County (Mont.)
Miles City (Mont.)
Montana
Agriculture
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Biographical Materials
  - Biographical sketches: Edward Charles "Teddy Blue" Abbott (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Ab-Am (includes Otto Hugo Abel, George Adams, Norval C. Adams, Robert Benjamin "Buzz" Aitchison, Nannie Alderson, Roy Alexander, Peter Allen, C.A. Allison, Frank Allison, James Allison, Ord Ames) (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: An-Ay (includes Amos Anderson, August Anderson, Claude Anderson, J.C. Anderson, Sarah Andrus, W.W. Andrus, Charles Appenzeller, Hubert P. Ambruster, James B. Armstrong, Virgil Arnett, William Asay, G.G. Askin, Robert Askin, John Atchison Jr., Toots Ayres) (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Ba (includes Lee Sherman "Shorty" Badgett, Charles H. Bahm, Henry Bailey, Leo Baldwin, Christina Ball, Oscar Ball, W.M. Bard, Fred H. Baringer, Martin Oliver Barnes, B.E. Barrett, Casey Barthelmess) (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Be-Bo (includes Jordan Bean, Robert Beason, W.R. "Baldy" Bement, Ben Bencine, Louis Benoist, Paul Bernard, David Bickle, Reginald Billing, Emil Bircher, Frank Bircher, Louis Bircher, Benton C. Bird, Les Boe, George Boggs, Charles M. Boucher, Dan H. Bowman, Henry O. Boyes, Neil Boyle) (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Br-Bu (includes George W. Bradley, William J. Bradshaw, Hilan Bray, John A. Broaddus, Oscar Broaddus, William Broaddus, George Brock, Charley Brown, Harry D. Brown, John H. Brown, Joseph T. Brown, O.J. Brownfield, Jimmy Bruce, Jay Bryan, Murt Buckley, Wilton "Fuzzy" Buffington, W.H. Bullard, John H. Burgess, Paul Burt, Grover Buster, Edmond Butler, Thomas Butler, John Butterfield) (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Ca (includes Lloyd Cain, Ira Calder, Hugh Calderwood, "Tut" Camblin, Oscar Canoy, John T. "Red" Carolan, David Carter, Peter Carter, Osceola C. Cato, Brit Catron, Robert Catron, William Edwin Caywood) (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Ch-Co (includes William Cherry, Richard G. Chilcote, John D. Childress, Phil Christenson, Alf Clark, Elmer W. Clark, Frank Clark, Raymond P. Colbert, Ray Coleman, George Colgan, Edward Collins, Ernest G. Coon, William Courtenay, Frank Cox, Mary Peachey Cox) (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Cr-Cu (includes Elmer E. Crawford, Leo Cremer, E. Frank Crosby, Emmett Crosby, Harvey H. "Hod" Crosby, Owen Crosby, William A. Crosby, C.R. "Bob" Cross, Francis Cross, Peter "Indian Pete" Culbertson, Lou L. Curl, William Curts, Benjamin Franklin Cusker) (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: D (includes Eben Daily, Harry Daily, Loren Daily, Sarah Daily, Heywood Daly, Ed H. Damm, Matt Damm, John Daut, Ephraim K. Davis, Frashier C. Davis, Howard E. Davis, James Davis, L.C. "Cornie" Davis, George W. Dearing, Charles F. Decker, Ross L. Decker, Charles De Graffenreid, Randolph Deibel, Richard W. Deibel re bombing of Hiroshima, Rene Delos, Edward Denton, James L. Dillard, Tom Dillard, Charles Divine, William Dominy, Stephen A. Douglass, Floyd Dowlin, Wynn E. Dowlin, Richard W. Dunn, Leonard Dunning, Hank Dykes) (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: E (includes Johnnie Earl, Ronnie H. Eaton, William K. Eaton, A.F. Edwards, Jack Edwards, Mert M. Edwards, Matt Elgin, Willis B. "Scotty" Embleton, Fred "Stub" Engels,William Ensley, Canute Erickson, Henry Hines Ervin, Harry Evans, R.L. "Bob" Ewing, Tom Ewing) (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: F (includes Hiram C. Farnum, George Farrell, John Fiel, Frank Fiske, Ole Flasted, John L. Flowers, James William Follis, Willis Forgey, Mert Francis, Alonzo H. "Lon" Frye, George Robert "Bob" Fudge, W.S. Fugate, Ernest Funk, Charles Furmer) (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: G (includes Daniel M. Gaskill, John Gibb, Jimmy Gibson, Loren W. Gilman, Dan Gilmore, Hiram Gilmore, Michael Dennis Gilmore, Tom Gilmore, Ernest Clay Gilpatrick, Emmett Glidewell, Dan Goodfellow, Sam Gordon, Charles H. Gould, Clifton Charles Green, Roy L. Griffin, Tag Grinnell) (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Ha (includes John H. Hallowell, Edward O. Halvorson, "Fatty" Hamilton, John T. Hamilton, Lionel Stratford Handcock, Frank B. Haney, William Hanify, Marion Lee Hanson, William Harmon, John Harrell, W.E. "Charlie" Harris, Joe Hawkes, James Ballou "Jack" Hawkins, William M. Hawkins, John Hays) (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: He-Hi (includes Charles H. Hedges, "Doc" Hedges, "J.P." Hedges, "Gum" Hedges, Elmer R. Heggen, George Helm, Emil Henning, J.W. "Jud" Hiscock, Font Hitchcock, Fred Hitzfeldt) (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Ho-Hy (includes Jack Hoffman, Ed Holbrook, Ernest Hollenshed, Arthur Holly, Harry Holman, Stephen "Rusty" Holman, John M. Holt, William Elmer Holt, Henry C. Holtkamp, Albert Holton, Humphrey Hood, Johnny Hoover, Jacob Horner, Samuel A. Hotchkiss, Samuel Houghland, F.P. Howe, W.L. Hughes, Hugh H. Hunter, William R. Hurley, B.C. Hutchinson, J.R. Hutchinson, James Weaver Hyde) (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: I (includes G.F. Ingersoll, G.I. Irion, Ray Irion) (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: J (includes Arthur L. Jellison, Cecilie Jensen, Nels Jensen, Peter Charles Jensen, Charles A. Johnson, E.H. "Skew" Johnson, Ernest E. Johnson, Sidney Johnson, Andrew Johnston, Johnny Johnstone, Andy Jones, Louis R. Jones, W.T. "Tom" Jones, Emmett Jordan, Frank Jordan, William A. "Allie" Jordan) (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: K (includes Hugh Kelly, Luther F. "Yellowstone" Kelly, Franklin T. Kelsey, Stanley Ketchel, Fred C. Kibler, Nils Kildahl, Frank Kincaid, Le Roy Kinsey, Carl Kraft, Carl A. Krutt, Hugh Kusker) (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: L (includes Howard T. Leister, Hugh Lemire, Ben Levalley, Daniel Levalley, Nels Lindeberg, Walter Lindsay, Dan Lockie, Dave Lockie, James Lockie, William Lockie, Charles D. Long, T. Whit Longley, Ralph Loop, Charles H. Loud, Edward Stanton Lower, R.L. Lowery, Elmer C. Lyndes) (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Ma (includes John B. Maclin, John Mahoney, Francis M. Malone, Andrew Malum, Steve Marmon, E.Z. Marks, Charles Marrs, B.F. Marsh, Charles Martin, Robert Martin, Tex Martin, Walter H. Martin) (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Mc (includes Tom McAlister, Curley McCale, William H. McCartney, Q.P. McClammy, W.A. McClammy, Walt McClatchy, Neece McCown, Joshua McCuiston, Alexander J. McCullough, A.L. McCurry, Alexander A. McDonald, Wilkin Craig McDowell, John McKay, Joseph R. McKay, Jud McKelvey, Horatio "Tug" McKelvey, Kenneth McLean, L.D. McMackin, William McNaney, Harry McNutt, William McVey (Box-folder 1 / 22)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Me-Mu (includes Earl Mead, Dwight Merwin, Charles W. Miles, George M. Miles, Henry A. Miller, Robert Milton, William Mitchell, Clyde Montgomery, Rufus E. Morris, W.P. Morse, Samuel N. Moses, George Mote, Clarence H. "Larry" Mott, Pat Mottram, James M. Mulkey, Roderick Munro, John Murnion, F.R. Murphy) (Box-folder 1 / 23)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: N (includes George Nelson, Olof Nelson, Curtis D. Newbary, G.D. Newman, Earl W. "Smoky" Nichols, Sol Nichols, Niels Nielsen) (Box-folder 1 / 24)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: O (includes Edward C. O'Connor, H.E. O'Donnell, Alex Ogilvie, June G. Olsen, John E. Olson, D.J. O'Malley, Frank D. O'Neill, Bruce Orcutt, O.T. O'Rien, Robert Colby Osgood) (Box-folder 1 / 25)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: P (includes Joseph James Packer, W.H. Paine, Charles Parker, Guy W. Parker, R.E. Patch, Ben Patton, John Pauley, W.G. Payne, David Peden, Earl Peden, Louis Pellieser, Gene Pendexter, Newt Perkins, Martin Petri, Freeman Philbrick, Malcolm Philbrick, Gilbert Powell, Don Pyle) (Box-folder 1 / 26)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Ra-Ri (includes Frank C. Raffaell, James G. Ramsay, Harry C. Reed, Ward M. Reid, Robert Rice, Pliney S. "Dick" Richardson, W. A. Richardson, William B. Richardson, Campbell G. "Mac" Rickard, Everett Ridge, Charlie Riley, Thomas Joe Riley, August Ritz) (Box-folder 1 / 27)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Ro-Ry (includes Albert "Bill" Roberts, Norman S. Robertson, Sion "Si" Robinson, A.E. Rodgers, Elmer Rodgers, Dan Rogers, John Fred Rogers, Mary Woody Rogers, Will Rogers, Pat Roney, Hugh Rooney, Frank Ross, Fred W. Rue, George Huntington Rue, Jasper S. Rue, Charles M. Russell, Harry Rutter, Paddy Ryan) (Box-folder 1 / 28)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Jesse Sales (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Sa-Si (includes F.B. Saddler, Charles P. Sanders, Roy Sankey, Harry "Tub" Schlosser, Ernest R. Schrader, Ed Schufelts, Charles L. Scofield, William H. Searls, W.A. Selvidge, Finley S. Sensiba, Jack Serruys, George Sherman Sr., Elton E. Shook, Ed B. Shriner, Dudley L. Shy, Ernest Ward Shy, Harry J. Siem, Charles Simpson, Charles Sims, James Sipes) (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Sl-Sw (includes Claude Henry Slater, Jack Sloan, Henry C. Smith, Michael Thomas Smith, Robert "Powder River Bob" Smith, Warren K. Smith, B.L. Snodgrass, Les Snodgrass, W.B. Spear, Paul Speck, Lorenzo W. Stacy, John Stafford, Kirk Stanley, John William Stephens, Lon Stewart, Herman Stoebe, Samuel Stoebe, August C. Stohr, Sam Stone, Charles Stuart, Walter F. Sumer, John Survant, Arby Swart) (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: T (includes Robert L. Tate, Edgar "Tuffy" Taylor, Howard Tennant, Courtenay Terrett, Charles Houston Thea, John Theade, Henry Clay Thompson, Lee Thorne, Sol Thorp, Guy Tibbetts, Lawrence A. Timberman, W.H. Timberman, John A. Tisdale, Floyd Tollefson, Matt Toohey, Edith Towers, Theron Townsend, Harve Trusler, Robert E. Lee Tucker, George Twible, Keith Twinning, W.A. Twitchell, [-----] Tysdall) (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: V (includes Marion P. Velk, Arthur J. Viall, Sid Vollin) (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Wa-Wh (includes J.L. Warren, Lewis R. "Lee" Warren, Chauncey R. Weaver, James Wescoe, George O. "Blocker" West, John Louis Wheeler, Edward Whitbeck, Guy Whitbeck, Dominick White) (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Wi-Wr (includes Pierre Wibaux, Dale Wilder, Charles Wiley, Gerald Willey, Fred E. Williams, John Williams, Roy C. Williams, Sidney A. Willis, Preston H. Willson, Al Wilson, Corrydon Wilson, S. Pat Wilson, Ernest Winning, Charles E. Winsor, Lee Wirth, Peter J. Witmayer, Benjamin Holt Woodcock, John W. Woodcock, Oscar Woods, Warren Woodson, Ed Wright, Lee Wright) (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: Y (includes Ed Yeager, Charles Yerkes, Robert Lee Yokley, Paul Young, William Young) (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Miles City area ranchers and cowboys: "Old Members" A-Z (includes brief notes about brands, where they worked, birth dates and places) (Box-folder 2 / 9)
- General Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous letters to Charles M. Boucher (includes letter to "old timers" soliciting biographical information, from nephew, True Magazine, Old Timers Roundup, Senator Ecton), 1944-1952, n.d. (Box-folder 2 / 10)
- Subject Files
  - Brands (includes Wyoming Stock Growers' Association brand book, Western Livestock Reporter brand sheets, notebook of brand information), 1882, 1948, n.d. (Box-folder 2 / 11)
- Writings
  - "Cave Hill Expedition," by Bill Stone (re 1883 South Dakota buffalo hunt), n.d. (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - "Chisholm Trail" by Charles Boucher, n.d. (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - "Introducing Historic Alzada," by Raymond Shelden (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - "Some Missourians Come West," by Charles Boucher, submitted to True Magazine, 1950 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
- Miscellany
  - "History" notebook (no order, includes some indexing) (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - "Lists" notebook (includes membership of Elks Lodge, lists of photographs, lists of brands) (Box-folder 2 / 17)
  - Miscellaneous notebook ("Brown section", includes brief biographical notes, history of Stoneville, sketch maps) (Box-folder 2 / 18)
  - Miscellaneous notebook ("Names and notes"; also includes politics, history, etc.) (Box-folder 2 / 19)
  - Miscellaneous notebook (includes historical notes, lists, indexes, etc.) (Box-folder 2 / 20)
  - Small notebooks (re politics, philosophy, history, biographical interviews, etc.; chronologically arranged, some are partially indexed), 1941, 1943-1949 (Box-folder 3 / 1-14)
  - Small notebooks (re politics, philosophy, history, biographical interviews, etc.; chronologically arranged, some are partially indexed), 1949-1952, n.d. (Box-folder 4 / 1-13)
  - Range Riders Roundup, Inc. articles of incorporation, 1939 (Box-folder 4 / 14)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous (re politics, history, western art, Range Riders reunion, etc.), 1939-1950, n.d. (Box-folder 4 / 15)
- Transfers to Other Programs
  - List of photographs transferred to Photo Archives (Box-folder 4 / 16)